Finding Aid for Mental Health Association in Michigan records, 1937-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mental Health Association in Michigan records 1937-2004, 1970-1990
Mental Health Association in Michigan.
12 linear feet
0567 Bf 2
Advocacy organization started in 1937 to promote awareness of mental health issues and lobby for patient rights. The record group documents the evolution of mental health care and legislative and organizational efforts to improve the field.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred by MHAM (donor no. 9563 ) to the Bentley Historical Library in February 2005.
The record group is open to research.
The Mental Health Association in Michigan began in 1937, and since that time has served as an advocacy organization for mental health issues. Even though it is not a government agency, the association has participated in crafting legislation and advising elected officials on topics related to mental health care. Originally called the Michigan Society for Mental Health, the organization has always viewed itself as working on behalf of both mental health care providers and consumers.
In 1944, MHAM obtained passage of the Michigan Visiting Teacher (school social worker) Act, which provided counseling for mentally ill children and their families.
During the next decade, the association rallied citizen support for a successful state bond issue referendum, which dramatically increased the number of state psychiatric hospital beds and provided funding for Hawthorn Center (for mentally ill children) and Lafayette Clinic (research, training, and care facility).
In 1952, MHAM became a participating member of the United Way of Michigan.
MHAM also obtained the first public appropriation (in the early 1960's) for community aftercare services in Michigan; initiated and marshaled the forces for enactment of the state's first Community Mental Health law (Public Act 54 of 1963) and the subsequent birth of the Michigan Association of Community Mental Health Boards.
The organization served as a catalyst for the modernization and humanization of state mental health statutes, resulting in passage of the landmark Michigan Mental Health Code (Public Act 258 of 1974).
In 1977, the Society changed its name to the Mental Health Association in Michigan.
In the next decade, MHAM drafted and introduced the legislation which eventually became the so-called "Children's Bill of 1984," governing the standards for voluntary admission and discharge of children to and from psychiatric hospitals. Not long afterwards, the association founded the self-help group Schizophrenics Anonymous, which has since spread across the country and abroad.
Beginning in 1990, MHAM established and conducted the first community-based monitoring programs of residential settings providing services to mentally ill persons.
Thee Mental Health Association in Michigan document the organization's efforts to promote and improve mental health care in the sate of Michigan. The record group includes correspondence, mailing, board and committee files, reports, files on annual meetings and regional meetings and workshops, MHAM publications and newsletters, and photographs. The records are arranged into the following series: Administrative Records, Conferences and Meetings, Newsletters, Reports, Site Visitation Program, Topical Files, Clippings, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Mental Health Association in Michigan.; Mental health services--Law and legislation--Michigan.; Mental health--Facilities--Michigan.; Mental health--Services--Michigan.; Mentally ill--Michigan.; People with mental disabilities--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Mental Health Association in Michigan.; Mental institutions--Michigan.; Mental health--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Administrative
  The Administrative Records (3 linear ft.) consist of mailings to the board of directors and executive committee, committee records, MHAM program files, and internal reports.
  - Committee Mailings
    - Board mailings 1972-April 1974 (Box 1)
    - Board mailings July 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee mailings 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee mailings 1975 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee mailings 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Board mailings 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee mailings 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Board mailings 1980-October 1981 (Box 1)
    - Board mailings November 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee mailings 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Board mailings 1983 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee mailings 1983 (Box 1)
    - Board and Executive Committee mailings 1984 (Box 1)
    - Board mailings 1985 (Box 1)
    - Board mailings 1986 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee mailings 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Board and Executive Committee mailings
      - 1987 (Box 1)
      - 1988 (Box 2)
      - 1989 (Box 2)
      - 1990 (Box 2)
      - 1991 (Box 2)
      - 1992 (Box 2)
      - 1993 (Box 2)
      - 1994 (Box 2)
      - 1995 (Box 2)
      - 1996 (Box 2)
    - Board mailings 1997 (Box 2)
    - Board mailings 1998 (Box 2)
    - Board and Executive Committee mailings 1999 (Box 2)
    - Board and Executive Committee mailings 2000 (Box 2)
  - Committees
    - Ad Hoc Committee to Review Community Mental Health Services in MI 1981 (Box 3)
    - Board Information 1967-1970 (Box 3)
    - Bylaw Revision Committee
      - 1982 (Box 3)
      - 1985-1987 (Box 3)
    - MHAM Managed Medicaid Work Group
      - Meetings and Correspondence December 1994-June 1995 (Box 3)
      - Meetings and Correspondence July 1995-March 1996 (Box 3)
      - Drafts and Reports 1995, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Mission Committee 1995 (Box 3)
    - Nominating Committee Reports 1978-1998 (Box 3)
    - Quality Care Task Force 1987 (Box 3)
    - School Mental Health Advisory Committee
      - 1954-1958 (Box 3)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - Site Visitation Committee 1988 (Box 3)
  - Programs
    - ACBL Charity of the Year Partnership 1979 (Box 3)
    - Any Place But Here Special December 1978 (Box 3)
    - Bequests (Box 3)
    - Child Advocacy 1969-1974 (Box 3)
    - Special Education (Box 3)
    - Webster-Kipfer Award (Box 3)
  - Reports
    - Mission Statement (Box 3)
    - Affirmative Action Plan 1978-1995 (Box 3)
    - Long Range Plans 1978-1995 (Box 3)
    - Program Goals 1989-1991 (Box 3)
    - Program of Work 1982-1990 (Box 3)
    - Achievement Report on Program of Work 1982-1990 (Box 3)
    - MHAM Position on Mental Health Issues 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Advertising Project 1978 (Box 3)
    - Member Survey on MHAM Goals and Programs
      - 1996 (Box 3)
      - 2001 (Box 3)
- Conferences and Meetings
  The Conferences and Meetings series (4 linear ft.) goes back to the beginning of the organization, with transcripts, programs, and speaker notes from annual conferences beginning in 1937. This series also includes meeting minutes from the board of directors and the executive committee.
  - Early Meetings
    - First Annual Business Meeting December 14, 1937
      - Program and Transcripts (Box 3)
      - Conference Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Newspaper Releases (Box 3)
      - Drafts of Programs (Box 4)
    - Second Annual Spring Conference April 7-8, 1938
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Program (Box 4)
      - Transcript (Box 4)
    - Michigan Conference of Social Work. Regional Meeting, Traverse City April 29-30, 1938 (Box 4)
    - Upper Peninsula Regional Conference October 7-8, 1938 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Conference of Social Work September 29-October 1, 1938 (Box 4)
    - Second Annual Business Meeting December 2, 1938 (Box 4)
    - Cadillac Study Lecture Series September 28, 1938-March 3, 1939 (Box 4)
    - Kalamazoo Mental Hygiene Institute March 22, 1939 (Box 4)
    - Third Annual Conference April 20-22, 1939
      - Program and Speakers (Box 4)
      - Publicity (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Kalamazoo Summer Mental Hygiene Institute July 17-21, 1939 (Box 4)
    - Third Annual Business Meeting November 10, 1939 (Box 4)
    - Saginaw Regional Conference March 6, 1940 (Box 4)
    - National Conference of Social Work May 1940 (Box 4)
    - Kalamazoo Mental Hygiene Institute September 19-21, 1940 (Box 4)
    - Annual Business Meeting 1940 (Box 4)
    - Annual Conference October 1940 (Box 4)
    - Annual Conference 1941
      - Program and Speakers (Box 4)
      - Publicity (Box 4)
    - Bay City Regional Conference April 30, 1941 (Box 5)
    - Traverse City Regional Meeting and Annual Meeting of State Hospital Commission May 22-23, 1941 (Box 5)
    - Annual Business Meeting October 3, 1941 (Box 5)
    - Kalamazoo Mental Hygiene Conference November 6-7, 1941 Jackson Conference, November 27-28, 1941 (Box 5)
    - Annual Business Meeting November 13, 1942 (Box 5)
    - Joint Annual Conference September 28-30, 1944 (Box 5)
    - Upper Peninsula Conference May 20-22, 1947 (Box 5)
  - Annual Conferences
    - 40th Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 29, 1977 (Box 5)
    - 41st Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 29, 1978 (Box 5)
    - 42nd Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 28, 1979 (Box 5)
    - 43rd Annual Membership Meeting and Conference 1980 (Box 5)
    - 44th Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 25, 1981 (Box 5)
    - 45th Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 10, 1982 (Box 5)
    - 46th Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 30, 1983 (Box 5)
    - 47th Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 28, 1984 (Box 5)
    - 48th Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 29, 1985 (Box 5)
    - 49th Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 26, 1986 (Box 5)
    - 50th Anniversary
      - Annual Meeting of the Membership October 1, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Anniversary Conference December 1987 (Box 5)
    - Special Meeting of the General Membership May 26, 1988 (Box 5)
    - 51st Annual Membership Meeting and Conference October 16, 1988 (Box 5)
    - 52nd Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 22, 1989 (Box 5)
    - 53rd Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 28, 1990 (Box 5)
    - 54th Annual Membership Meeting and Conference September 13, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Annual Meeting of the Membership October 1, 1993 (Box 5)
    - 57th Annual Membership Meeting and Conference June 13, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Annual Meeting of the General Membership 1995 (Box 5)
    - Annual Meeting
      - May 3, 1996 (Box 5)
      - May 17, 1997 (Box 5)
      - June 5, 1998 (Box 5)
      - June 4, 1999 (Box 5)
      - May 19, 2000 (Box 5)
      - May 11, 2001
        - Program and Speakers (Box 6)
        - Member Survey (Box 6)
      - May 7, 2002 (Box 6)
  - Executive Committee Meetings
    - February 12, 1992 (Box 6)
    - April 22, 1992 (Box 6)
    - September 23, 1992 (Box 6)
    - September 29, 1992 (Box 6)
    - MI Coalition 1992 (Box 6)
    - January 20, 1993 (Box 6)
    - April 19, 1993 (Box 6)
    - August 31, 1993 (Box 6)
    - February 11, 1994 (Box 6)
    - November 2, 1994 (Box 6)
    - February 22, 1995 (Box 6)
    - May 10, 1995 (Box 6)
    - September 13, 1995 (Box 6)
    - November 8, 1995 (Box 6)
    - February 21, 1996 (Box 6)
    - May 15, 1996 (Box 6)
    - August 28, 1996 (Box 6)
    - January 22, 1997 (Box 6)
    - April 23, 1997 (Box 6)
    - August 20, 1997 (Box 6)
    - November 5, 1997 (Box 6)
    - February 18, 1998 (Box 6)
    - April 22, 1998 (Box 6)
    - September 16, 1998 (Box 6)
    - November 4, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Board of Directors Meetings
    - Board Retreat October 2-3, 1982, November 4, 1982 (Box 6)
    - December 5, 1985 (Box 6)
    - March 27, 1986 (Box 6)
    - June 13, 1986 (Box 6)
    - Board/Staff Retreat June 13-14, 1986 (Box 6)
    - October 23, 1986 (Box 6)
    - December 4, 1986 (Box 6)
    - March 12, 1987 (Box 6)
    - May 21, 1987 (Box 6)
    - October 1, 1987 (Box 6)
    - December 3, 1987 (Box 6)
    - March 10, 1988 (Box 6)
    - September 22, 1988 (Box 6)
    - December 8, 1988 (Box 6)
    - February 16, 1989 (Box 6)
    - May 25, 1989 (Box 6)
    - September 22, 1989 (Box 6)
    - December 7, 1989 (Box 7)
    - March 1, 1990 (Box 7)
    - June 1, 1990 (Box 7)
    - June 27, 1990 (Box 7)
    - September 27, 1990 (Box 7)
    - December 6, 1990 (Box 7)
    - February 28, 1991 (Box 7)
    - May 22, 1991 (Box 7)
    - September 12, 1991 (Box 7)
    - December 2, 1991 (Box 7)
    - February 21, 1992 (Box 7)
    - May 21, 1992 (Box 7)
    - September 23, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Board Reorganization October 2, 1992 (Box 7)
    - December 4, 1992 (Box 7)
    - March 18, 1993 (Box 7)
    - My 27 1993 (Box 7)
    - October 1, 1993 (Box 7)
    - December 2, 1993 (Box 7)
    - March 18, 1994 (Box 7)
    - June 13, 1994 (Box 7)
    - September 22, 1994 (Box 7)
    - December 8, 1994 (Box 7)
    - March 9, 1995 (Box 7)
    - June 5, 1995 (Box 7)
    - September 28, 1995 (Box 7)
    - December 7, 1995 (Box 7)
    - March 7, 1996 (Box 7)
    - May 3, 1996 (Box 7)
    - September 12, 1996 (Box 7)
    - December 12, 1996 (Box 7)
    - March 20, 1997 (Box 7)
    - May 17, 1997 (Box 7)
    - September 11, 1997 (Box 7)
    - December 4, 1997 (Box 8)
    - March 19, 1998 (Box 8)
    - October 1, 1998 (Box 8)
- Newsletters
  The Newsletters series (0.5 linear ft.) contains newsletters produced by MHAM, including the Mental Health Bulletin which began in 1938.
  - Advocate
    - 1973-June 1975 (Box 8)
    - Fall 1975-1978 (Box 8)
    - 1979-1988 (Box 8)
  - Department of Mental Health News Brief 1987-1988 (Box 8)
  - Issues in Mental Health Care 1993-1994 (Box 8)
  - Mental Health Bulletin
    - 1938-1942 (Box 8)
    - 1943-1950 (Box 8)
    - 1951-1960 (Box 8)
    - 1961-1973 (Box 8)
  - News and Views Legislative Update 1977-1987 (Box 8)
  - Society at Work 1957-1963 (Box 8)
  - Prevention Pieces 1985-1987 (Box 8)
- Reports
  The Reports series (0.5 linear ft.) includes reports on mental health topics by MHAM and governmental agencies.
  - Citizen Opinion Studies on Mental Health Issues 1987-1990 (Box 8)
  - MHAM Annual Report 1984, 1985 (Box 8)
  - Mental Disability Prevention 1986, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Mental Health Services for Children 1964, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Project Reports 1957-1960, 1989-1990 (Box 8)
  - Reports on Mental Health Topics for Public Education 1967-1993 (Box 8)
  - Report and Recommendations on Mental Health Issues 1984-1989 (Box 8)
- Site Visitation
  The Site Visitation series (1 linear ft.) documents MHAM's program to provide citizen oversight of mental health institutions. It includes overall evaluation of the program, volunteer training materials, and observation reports on the facilities visited.
  - Site Visitation Program
    - Program Evaluation and Overview 1985-1987 (Box 8)
    - Findings and Recommendations for all MI Hospitals 1988-1989 (Box 8)
    - Overview of MI Mental Health Care Concerns 1987 (Box 9)
    - Program Correspondence (Box 9)
    - Fairlawn Center 1985-1987 (Box 9)
  - Clinton Valley Center
    - Overview of Organization and Services 1986 (Box 9)
    - Programs 1986-1987, undated (Box 9)
    - Citizen Advisory Council Minutes
      - 1984-1986 (Box 9)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence 1985-1986 (Box 9)
    - Department of Mental Health Audit Report 1983-1985 (Box 9)
    - Detailed Visitation Reports and CVC Responses 1985-1986 (Box 9)
    - Visitation Results 1985-1987 (Box 9)
    - Volunteer Recruitment and Training (Box 9)
    - Volunteer Feedback Surveys March 1987 (Box 9)
  - Northville Regional Psychiatric Hospital
    - Program Overview, Roles and Responsibilities (Box 9)
    - Organization Overview and Manuals (Box 9)
    - Citizen's Advisory Council Meeting Minutes 1986-1990 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence 1986-1989 (Box 9)
    - Newsletters 1986-1987 (Box 9)
    - Ward Observations 1984-1989 (Box 9)
    - Responses to Ward Observations 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Site Visitation Summary 1987-1988 (Box 9)
    - Biannual Summary Reports, August, 24 1987-February 24, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Monthly Comprehensive Reports 1989-1991 (Box 9)
    - Responses to Ward Observations 1989 (Box 9)
    - Ward Observations 1990-1991 (Box 10)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (2.2 linear ft.) consists of materials on a variety of topics relating to mental health and MHAM.
  - Burnout (Box 10)
  - Children and Violence (Box 10)
  - Citizen Involvement in State Mental Institutions 1977 (Box 10)
  - Crowley's Christmas Angel Program 1979-1982 (Box 10)
  - Deinstitutionalization (Box 10)
  - Department of Mental Health (Box 10)
  - Depression (Box 10)
  - Domestic Violence (Box 10)
  - Emotional Survival Kit 1979-1980 (Box 10)
  - Funding for Mental Health Care 1981-1982 (Box 10)
  - Glossary of Mental Health Terms (Box 10)
  - Health Care Financing Administration Grant 1991 (Box 10)
  - Health Care Reform 1994-1995 (Box 10)
  - Heart of Gold Award 1990, 2001 (Box 10)
  - Homeless Mentally Ill (Box 10)
  - Juvenile Code 1942-1947 (Box 10)
  - Logos and Artwork (Box 10)
  - Lafayette Clinic
    - Articles and Reports (Box 10)
    - Correspondence and Meetings (Box 10)
    - Training and Research Lawsuit (Box 10)
    - 25th Anniversary (Box 10)
    - Laws-MI 1949-1952 (Box 10)
  - Legislative Issues 1960-1973, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Legislative Reports on Community Placement 1974 (Box 11)
  - Mental Health Code
    - Mental Health Commission 1961-1962 (Box 11)
    - Public Act 54 1963 (Box 11)
    - Revisions 1971-1973 (Box 11)
    - Amendments 1974, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Public Act 258 1974-1975 (Box 11)
    - Revisions 1974-1976 (Box 11)
    - Official Code 1976, 1979 (Box 11)
  - Michigan Association of Community Mental Health Boards 1973-1974 (Box 11)
  - MHA in Marinette and Menominee Counties 1993-1997 (Box 11)
  - MHA in Muskegon 1999 (Box 11)
  - Mental Health Month (Box 11)
  - MHAM Early Promotional Materials (Box 11)
  - Patient Rights 1982-1988 (Box 11)
  - Prescription Drug User Fee Act 1997 (Box 11)
  - Public Policy Positions 1974-1985 (Box 11)
  - Resolutions 1980-1991, undated (Box 11)
  - Schizophrenics Anonymous 1990-1999 (Box 11)
  - Self-Esteem (Box 11)
  - Chris Sizemore, multiple personalities 1987-1990 (Box 12)
  - United Way of Michigan
    - Agency Policies 1991 (Box 12)
    - Agency Agreements 1987-1991 (Box 12)
    - Funding Changes 2001 (Box 12)
    - MHAM Site Visit 1995 (Box 12)
    - MHAM Site Visit 1996 (Box 12)
    - MHAM Site Visit 1997 (Box 12)
    - MHAM Site Visit 1998 (Box 12)
    - Presentation to MHAM 1998 (Box 12)
  - Very Special Arts Program 1996 (Box 12)
- Clippings
  The Clippings series (0.4 linear ft.) contains newspaper articles on mental health topics.
  - Biographical articles, MHAM affiliates 1965-1967 (Box 12)
  - Case Studies 1981-1982 (Box 12)
  - Children's Hospital 1952-1953 (Box 12)
  - Funding for Mental Health Care 1950-1987 (Box 12)
  - Hospitalization and Community-Based Care 1966-1987 (Box 12)
  - Mental Health Maze-Detroit Free Press Series on Mental Health in MI 1977-1978 (Box 12)
  - Mental Health and the Public 1953-1999 (Box 12)
  - Mental Illness and the Courts 1974-1985 (Box 12)
  - Mentally Ill Viewpoints 1982, undated (Box 12)
  - Northville Regional Psychiatric Hospital 1982-1985 (Box 12)
  - Schizophrenia 1972-1986 (Box 12)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series (0.4 linear ft.) includes photos of MHAM events such as conferences, meetings, and awards ceremonies. Many local mental health institutions have also been photographed. This series also contains a training video for the site visitation program.
  - Photographs
    - Awards (Box 12)
    - Conferences (Box 12)
    - Institutions (Box 12)
    - Meetings (Box 12)
    - Meetings with the Governor (Box 12)
    - Oakland Annual Meeting (Box 12)
    - Portraits (Box 12)
    - Publicity (Box 12)
  - Videotape
    - Site Visitation Training 1985 (Box 12)